Preliminary Guide to the Nicholas Georgescu-Roegen Papers, 1944-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nicholas Georgescu-Roegen papers 1944-1994
Georgescu-Roegen, Nicholas
44 linear feet Extent: 33002 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
georgescuroegen
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library received the Nicholas Georgescu-Roegen papers as a gift in 1995 and 2000.
Biographical Note
Noted economist and professor at Vanderbilt University; formerly from Romania.
Collection Overview
The original accession (33000 items, dated 1944-1994) includes correspondence, research and writings, subject files, teaching materials, and autobiographical writings documenting the life and career of economist Nicholas Georgescu-Roegen (1906-1994). Correspondents include the economists Joseph Schumpeter (under whom he studied at Harvard) and Friedrich von Hayek. Topics include analytical economics, value theory and consumer behavior, bio-economics, time and economic change, entropy and its application to economics, agricultural economics, and the teaching of economics. Some materials are in Russian or Romanian. There are a few photographs of Georgescu-Roegen.
Typed transcripts and other documents reveal details concerning political conditions in Romania during the period of the provisional government and the Armistice trials following World War II (1944-1945). During this period Georgescu-Roegen served the new government in various capacities before he fled the country with his wife in 1948. The accession also includes about 40 audio tape (reel-to-reel) recordings. (95-025)
The addition to the collection (2 items, dated 1950-1975), includes class notes by students in Georgescu-Roegen's course, "Introduction to Mathematical Economics," spring 1950, at Vanderbilt and an audio tape recording (reel-to-reel) of dinner talks given on October 24, 1975, during a two-day conference at Vanderbilt recognizing Georgescu-Roegen's accomplishments. Speakers included Chancellor Heard of Vanderbilt and economists Paul Samuelson and Joseph Spengler. (00-425)
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Georgescu-Roegen, Nicholas; Samuelson, Paul Anthony, 1915-; Schumpeter, Joseph Alois, 1883-1950; Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-; Time and economic reactions.; Value; Entropy; Economic development -- Environmental aspects; Consumer behavior; Economics, Mathematical.; Economics -- Study and teaching.; Agriculture -- Economic aspects; Economists Correspondence; World War, 1939-1945 -- Romania; Romania -- History -- 1944-1989; Romania -- Politics and government.; Audio tapes.
Contents of Collection
- Accession 95-025
  - Correspondence by personal name, 1960s-1980s, A-E (Box 1)
  - "Fan Mail," 1950s-1980s
  - Correspondence by personal name, 1960s-1980s, F-M. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence by personal name, 1960s-1980s, M-Z (Box 3)
  - Photographs
  - Correspondence, Vanderbilt and Romania (Box 4)
  - Personal correspondence
  - "Selected older or important letters," (Schumpeter, Hayek, etc.)
  - Correspondence by organizations, 1960s-1980s, A-W. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence by subject, 1960s-1990s (some alphabetical arrangement). (Box 6)
  - Correspondence and other materials by place-name, 1960s-1990s, A-W. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1950s-1980s, C-S (Box 8)
  - Various correspondence dated by years, 1986-1994
  - Place-name files (Princeton, Harvard, Sao Paolo), 1960s-1970s
  - Correspondence (Box 9)
  - Articles
  - Invitations
  - Autobiographical writings (Box 10)
  - My Life Philosophy
  - Writings by NGR (typescripts)
  - Correspondence (Box 11)
  - Articles
  - Articles (chiefly by other authors) (Box 12)
  - Publications and periodicals files (Box 13)
  - Addresses
  - Curriculum vitae files
  - Lectures, statistics (Box 14)
  - Free Europe Handbook (on Romania)
  - Russian Research Center, Harvard, 1949
  - Research grant files
  - Writings on Romania by NGR and others (Box 15)
  - Typed transcripts and copies of Romanian Armistice trials and other meetings related to provisional government (1944-1945)
  - Maps
  - Writings: Romania (Box 16)
  - Writings: Romania, Basarabia (Box 17)
  - Writings: Time and evolution; time and change; time in economics; analytical economics; theory and economic reality; plant, firm, industry; value theory and the consumer's behavior; value theory and the consumer's behavior; logical and empirical foundations fo economic development (ch. 1-7)
  - Various notes
  - Crivelli on NGR, 1987
  - Statistics files
  - Statistics and econometrics files (Box 18)
  - Tests and exams on economic theory
  - Writings: Drafts and notes on peasant economy (Box 19)
  - Manuscript fragments
  - Notes: Psychology and economics and other topics (Box 20)
  - Writings: Utility, Gossen, economy and ethics, bioeconomics and ethics, man and production, the energetic theory of economic value, satiety
  - Phyllis Jenkin (Box 21)
  - Jeremy Rifkin
  - Gossen
  - Writings: Structural unemployment, Romania, Basarabia (Box 22)
  - Writings by other authors [often related to NGR's works, with letters to him] (Box 23)
  - Writings and notes by NGR: Romania, Atlanta, Milano (Box 24)
  - Matzner, Egon
  - Writings by NGR (Box 25)
  - Writings by NGR (Box 26)
  - Notebooks containing published writings by NGR in chronological order (Box 27)
  - Notebooks containing articles about NGR and review of his works (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and subject files (Koide, Myernik, etc.) (Box 29)
  - Audiotapes from Vanderbilt office [possibly lectures by NGR]
  - Audiotapes from Vanderbilt office [possibly lectures by NGR] (Box 30)